we're continuing to study Spinners from
a mathematical point of view and in this
video we're going to discuss the
difference between Paulie Spinners vial
Spinners and direct spinners
the short answer is that powley Spinners
are two component objects associated
with 3D space vial Spinners are two
component objects associated with 4D
space-time and direct Spinners are four
component Spinners associated with 4D
space-time made up of a left chiral vial
spinner and a right chiral vial spinner
stacked on top of each other
we've spent the last few videos
discussing powley Spinners in detail in
this video we're going to discuss all
the differences between Paulie Spinners
and vial spinners
once we understand the two component
file Spinners it will be very easy to
understand the four component direct
Spinners since a direct spinner is
simply a pair of vial spinners
to begin I'm going to give an overview
of all the differences between Pali
Spinners and vial Spinners and then I'll
spend the rest of this video exploring
the differences in detail
in 3D space we calculate the squared
length of a vector using Pythagoras's
Theorem x squared plus y squared plus Z
squared in 4D space time we instead
calculate the square of the space-time
interval s squared which is time squared
minus the space component squared
the length of 3D vectors is held
constant during rotations done with SO3
matrices
the space-time interval of 4D space-time
vectors is held constant when we do
Lorenz Transformations done with so13
matrices
we can rewrite 3D vectors as two by two
matrices called Pali vectors and we can
rewrite 4D space-time vectors as two by
two matrices called vial vectors
Paulie vectors are rotated with
double-sided Transformations with su2
matrices vial vectors are lorentz
transformed with double-sided
Transformations with sl2c matrices
Pauly vectors can be factored into a
pair of Pali Spinners and vial vectors
can be factored into a pair of vial
spinners
the inner product of Paulie Spinners is
Sci dagger PSI but the inner product of
vile Spinners is side transposed times
the Epsilon Matrix times PSI
Pali Spinners don't have a notion of
chirality but vile Spinners can be
either left chiral or right chiral
finally powley Spinners have two types
of indices four Spinners and dual
Spinners vial Spinners have four types
of indices for the left and right
versions of spinners and dual spinners
to begin let's do a quick review of
special relativity if this review goes
too fast I've included some links in the
description that cover special
relativity more slowly
in Galilean relativity a space-time
diagram with time along the vertical
axis looks like a sequence of
photographs that change as we move up
along the time axis we can change our
frame of reference just by sliding these
photographs left and right
this means that light beams can have any
speed and Galilean relativity because
changing our reference frame will change
the speed of light
special relativity postulates that the
speed of light C is the same in all
inertial reference frames this means we
need a new way to change our frame of
reference that keeps these two beams of
light unchanged
the key to changing reference frames
while keeping the speed of light
constant is squashing space time along
one beam of light and extending it along
the other beam of light
this change of coordinates is called a
lorentz boost and it is given by this
formula here
it can also be written with hyperbolic
trig functions
so lorentz boosts are actually
hyperbolic rotations
you'll also notice I've written the time
variable as the speed of light c times
time this is a common convention in
special relativity because it gives time
units of distance which allows us to
treat time and space together on equal
footing in space time
this brings us to the first Topic in
this chart comparing length in 3D space
to the space-time interval in 4D space
time
in 2D physical space we measure length
using the Pythagoras formula involving a
sum of squares x squared plus y squared
equals r squared a curve of constant R
is called a circle and R is the circle's
radius
in 2D space-time we measure a distance
like quantity using the formula
involving a difference of squares time
squared minus space squared equals s
squared where s is called the space time
interval
a curve of constant s is called a
hyperbola unlike length squared which is
either positive or zero s squared can
also be negative
when s squared is positive we call it a
time like hyperbola
when s squared is negative we call it a
space like hyperbola
when s squared is zero the time
coordinate equals the space coordinate
and this traces out the straight line
Paths of light beams
these curves have many different names
such as null isotropic or lights like
curves
in three-dimensional space the squared
length formula looks like this and in
four-dimensional space time the
space-time interval squared formula
looks like this
next we'll talk about the matrices used
to rotate in 3D space and Lorenz
transform in 4D space time
in 3D space the squared length of a
vector v is given by V transpose V
a transformation r that keeps the length
constant must satisfy R transpose equals
R inverse we say R belongs to the group
O three the three by three orthogonal
matrices these include both rotations
with determinant plus one and reflected
rotations with determinant minus one
if we want to restrict ourselves to
rotations only we force the determinant
to be plus one we call these
Transformations SO3 the 3X3 special
orthogonal matrices
a rotation always pushes points along a
circle in a plane which is defined by a
pair of variables
we can find all the basic rotation types
by looking at all the possible pairs of
coordinate variables which are x y y z
and ZX
so there are three basic types of
rotations which are done with matrices
involving cosines and Sines
in 4D space-time the squared space-time
interval of a vector W is given by W
transpose ETA W where ETA is this Matrix
called the mankowsky metric
multiplying this out gives the familiar
time squared minus space squared formula
we saw earlier
a transformation Lambda that keeps s
squared constant must satisfy Lambda
transpose ETA Lambda equals ETA
we say Lambda belongs to the group 013
the orthogonal group in one time
Dimension and three space dimensions
if we want to ignore spatial Reflections
we force the determinant to be plus one
which gives us the special orthogonal
group so13
if we want to forbid Reflections in time
which swaps the past and the future we
also need to demand that the top left
member of the Lambda Matrix is positive
this is called the ortho Cronus
condition denoted with a plus
these Transformations that keep s
squared constant are called Lorenz
transformations
basic lorentz Transformations also take
place in a plane defined by a pair of
variables
we can find all basic lorentz
Transformations by looking at all
possible pairs of coordinate variables
these are x y y z z x t x t y and t z so
there are six basic Lorenz
transformations
three of these are the 3D spatial
rotations we've already seen
the other three are lorentz boosts which
move us to a new reference frame with
some constant velocity
in our s squared formula if we set time
and the third space coordinate to zero
we get the familiar equation of a circle
and we rotate circles using cosines and
Sines with matrices like these
but we also have three boosts which
match up the time variable and a space
variable
if we set two of the space variables to
zero we get the equation of a hyperbola
we transform hyperbolas with lorentz
boosts also called hyperbolic rotations
with hyperbolic cosine and hyperbolic
sine
these are given by these matrices here
so let's start our comparison between
Paulie Spinners and vial Spinners by
talking about vial vectors
with 3D vectors we found that if we
replaced the basis vectors by Pauly
matrices we ended up with a two by two
Matrix called a Paoli Vector which is
another way of representing a 3D vector
for 4D space-time vectors we do
something similar except we replace the
time basis Vector with the identity
Matrix which I'm writing as this fancy
number one
this can also be written as Sigma t or
Sigma 0.
this gives us a two by two Matrix
representation of a 4D space-time vector
I've never seen this Matrix given an
official name so for this video series
I'm going to call it a vial vector
now how do we know this is the correct
way of representing a 4D space-time
Vector as a two by two Matrix
well for Pali vectors when we took the
determinant we got the formula for the
negative squared length of the vector
let's see what happens when we take the
determinant of a vial vector
we get two products which we can
distribute and since these inner terms
cancel we get time squared minus the
squares of the three space components
this equals the square of the space-time
interval for this vector
so this is a good indication that our
vial Vector is the correct way of
representing a space-time Vector as a
two by two Matrix because its
determinant tells us the vectors
space-time interval
now let's consider the double-sided
transformation of vial vectors
now we know that 3D vectors rotate with
SO3 matrices and in video number six in
this series we learned that we can do an
equivalent rotation on Paulie vectors by
acting on it with a double-sided
transformation of su2 matrices the
special unitary 2x2 matrices
these matrices each do half the rotation
and so they use half angles of theta
over two
it's worth asking if we can do something
similar in space time
we know 4D space-time vectors can be
lorentz transformed with so13 matrices
if we rewrite our space-time vectors as
two by two vial vectors we can ask if
there's a similar double-sided
transformation that we can do to achieve
lorentz transformations
we knew that poly vectors were hermitian
and so they should remain hermitian
after a 3D rotation with a double-sided
transformation involving matrices A and
B
this led us to conclude that b must
equal a dagger the hermitian conjugate
of a
and so a Pali vector v is rotated using
the transformation
Ava dagger
vial vectors are also hermitian and so
if we do a lorentz transformation using
a double-sided Matrix transformation the
result should also be hermitian
and we conclude we lorentz transform a
vile Vector W using the transformation
AWA dagger
we also knew that the determinant of a
Paulie Vector is the vector's negative
squared length
since rotations don't change the length
of a vector we concluded that the
determinant of the a matrix must have
magnitude one
we also saw that these double-sided
Transformations allow for arbitrary
phase shifts in the a matrix without
changing the rotation result so it was
always possible to pick a phase shift
that sets the determinant of a to
positive one
the determinant of a vial Vector is the
square of the vector's space-time
interval which is unchanged under Lorenz
transformations
so we can also conclude that the
determinant of a has magnitude 1. in the
case of lorentz transforming vial
vectors and we can force this
determinant to be plus one using the
phase shift property
finally we observed that Paulie vectors
had zero trace and we used this fact to
prove that the transformation matrices
on Pali vectors must be unitary
however vial vectors can have non-zero
Trace so we cannot guarantee that the
matrices transforming vial vectors are
unitary
so poly vectors rotate with this
double-sided transformation
I'm going to rewrite the a matrix as U
for clarity
U is a two by two Matrix with
determinant plus one so it is special
The Matrix is also unitary
so Paulie vectors rotate with special
unitary two by two matrices also called
su2 matrices
vial vectors are lorentz transformed
with a double-sided transformation and
I'm going to rewrite the a matrix as L
for clarity
L is a two by two Matrix with
determinant plus one so the Matrix is
special
but there is no requirement for these
transformation matrices to be unitary so
these are the special linear two by two
matrices SL2
since we're dealing with complex numbers
we often write a letter C to tell us
that the Matrix elements are complex
instead of real
so vial vectors are lorentz transformed
with double-sided Transformations with
sl2c matrices
in video number six we found that su2
matrices are defined by two complex
numbers Alpha and beta this gives us
four real numbers but since the
determinant is plus one this gives one
additional real constraint reducing the
number of free parameters to three real
numbers this corresponds to the three
possible rotations in 3D space
if we look at an sl2c Matrix we have
four complex numbers or eight real
numbers
but since the determinant is forced to
be plus one this gives us two additional
real constraints where the determinants
magnitude must be one and its phase must
be zero this reduces the number of free
parameters to six real numbers
this corresponds to the three possible
rotations and three possible boosts in
4D space time
recall from video number six that we
could get Su 2 matrices using these half
angle formulas involving cosine and sine
we just multiply the sine term by a pair
of sigmas that indicate the plane of
rotation
we can do something similar for boosts
but using hyperbolic cosine and
hyperbolic sign and we multiply the sine
H term using Sigma T which is the
identity Matrix and the sigma for the
direction we're boosting in
now let's talk about factoring these two
by two matrices into spinners
with Paulie vectors we found that it was
sometimes possible to factor them into a
column and a row called Paulie Spinners
with the column being a spinner and the
row being a dual spinner
there were multiple solutions to this
factoring since we could always get a
new solution if we multiplied the column
by a number K and multiplied the row by
1 over k
but the most straightforward solution is
given by these formulas
however we found this factoring could
only be done if the determinant of the
Matrix was Zero
and in order for this factoring to be
done we need either all the XYZ
components to be zero or at least some
of them to be complex numbers it's
impossible to do this factoring if all
the components are real and non-zero
now let's try factoring a vial Vector
into a column and a row which will
require the determinant to be zero
since the space-time interval formula
contains both positive and negative
terms it's possible to make the
space-time interval equal zero using
only real components so complex numbers
are not required
remember the space-time interval
equaling 0 means the vector is null or
isotropic also called light like since
it points along the direction of travel
of a light beam in space time
so let's take a vial vector and assume
its determinant the square of the
space-time interval is zero we'll also
assume all the components are real
numbers
in order to factor it into a column and
a row we need to solve for these values
a b c d
multiplying the column by the row and
comparing the results with the Matrix
entries we get these four equations
now remember all four space-time
components are real numbers so time plus
Z must be real this means that a times C
must be real as well
the only way for this to be true is if C
equals the complex conjugate of a times
some real Factor K1
we also know that time minus said must
be real so D must equal the complex
conjugate of B times some real Factor K2
looking at the other two equations we
see that the right hand sides are
complex conjugates of each other which
means that the left sides must also be
complex conjugates of each other
if we sub in our formulas for C and D we
can cancel A and B conjugate and that
gives us K1 equals K2 since they are
both real
the real number K is just an arbitrary
scaling factor that we can set to one
basically if a vector points in a light
like Direction with a space-time
interval 0 multiplying it by a scale
factor won't change the direction and it
will still have a space-time interval of
zero so we'll just take k equals one for
Simplicity
but we still need to solve for the
complex numbers A and B
iven these four formulas notice that if
we add the first two together the time
components add and the Z components
cancel if we divide by two we get a
formula for time in terms of A and B
we can get an equation for Z if we
subtract the two formulas instead and we
can get similar formulas for X and Y by
adding and subtracting the other two
formulas
so this gives us the space-time
components in terms of the spinner
components but how do we get the spinner
components from the space-time
components
we can think of the complex numbers A
and B as each being defined by a
magnitude and a phase
from equation one we see the magnitude
of a is the square root of time plus Z
likewise from equation 2 the magnitude
of B is the square root of time minus
said
from equation 3 Let's divide both sides
by the magnitudes of A and B which we
can rewrite as these square roots on the
right hand side
on the left hand side a complex number
divided by its magnitude just gives its
phase
combining the exponents this gives us
the phase difference between a and b
on the right hand side we can multiply
the square roots to get the square root
of time squared minus Z squared for a
null Vector this also equals the square
root of x squared plus y squared
so even though there are four real
numbers in this spinner we can only
solve for three the two magnitudes and
one phase difference this is because the
four space time components for a null
Vector only have three free parameters
the fourth parameter is determined by
the other three so we can only get three
parameters for the Spinners any overall
phase Factor will get canceled out when
we multiply the Spinners together so
overall phase factors don't impact the
final results
so we've successfully factored a null
vial Vector into a vial spinner and a
dual vial spinner
from now on I'll label the components of
a vial spinner as PSI 1 and PSI 2 with
upper indices
if we rotate a powley vector using a
pair of su2 matrices and then Factor our
poly Vector into a pair of Pali Spinners
we see that the column spinner rotates
with a single half angle su2 Matrix
acting from the left and we see that our
row dual spinner transforms with the
hermitian conjugate of this half angle
su2 Matrix acting from the right
similarly if we lorentz transform a vial
Vector using a double-sided sl2c
transformation and then Factor it into a
pair of vial Spinners we see that the
column spinner transforms with a single
sl2c Matrix from the left and the row
dual spinner transforms with the
hermitian conjugate of this sl2c Matrix
from the right
now let's talk about inner products
Loosely speaking the inner product of
two vectors tells us the angle between
them and the inner product of a vector
with itself tells us the vector's
squared length
the reason inner products are useful is
that they don't change under rotations
for example if we take the inner product
of vectors u and v written U transpose V
and rotate them both with an SO3 Matrix
R since the transpose of an SO3 Matrix
equals its inverse these cancel to the
identity meaning the inner product is
unchanged
similarly if we take two Paulie Spinners
PSI and Chi and take their inner product
PSI dagger Chi when we rotate them with
su2 matrices we end up with u dagger u
in the middle
and Since U is unitary U dagger equals U
inverse so these cancel to the identity
meaning the inner product is unchanged
now if we take two vial Spinners PSI and
Phi we might hope that PSI dagger Phi is
unchanged under Lorenz Transformations
but this turns out to be not true if we
transform our vile Spinners with an sl2c
Matrix called L this is not guaranteed
to be unitary so this l dagger l in the
middle will not always be the identity
Matrix so this is not a good inner
product for vial Spinners and we need a
new inner product formula
the inner product is often written as a
row times a column but we can get more
interesting inner products if we put a
matrix in the middle between them for
example the inner product in flat space
time uses this Matrix here with a
positive one and three negative ones
along the diagonal this Matrix is called
the mankowsky metric and is usually
written as Ada
we can try to find a similar Matrix
Epsilon that goes in between a pair of
vial Spinners which will give us a good
inner product
if I Lorenz transform the Spinners with
an sl2c Matrix L and set the inner
product equal to the original formula I
end up with the constraint that l dagger
Epsilon L must equal Epsilon
it turns out that there is no Epsilon
Matrix that will satisfy this formula
for arbitrary l so it doesn't give us a
good inner product
however if I start over and use PSI
transpose instead of PSI dagger I get
the constraint L transpose Epsilon L
equals Epsilon and it turns out this can
give us a good inner product
if I write this as a matrix equation
where L has components Alpha Beta Gamma
Delta and churn through the Matrix
multiplications I get four equations
constraining the components of Epsilon
these equations must be true for any
choice of Alpha Beta Gamma Delta as long
as they're determinant equals one
looking at equation one the right hand
side only has the component Epsilon 1 1.
this means Epsilon 2 2 must go to zero
the middle term must also go to zero
telling us that Epsilon 2 1 equals
negative Epsilon 1 2. and finally
Epsilon 1 1 must also be zero since the
equation must be true for any Alpha
so we have these constraints on the
components of Epsilon the simplest
solution is to pick Epsilon 1 2 equaling
1 which gives us this Epsilon Matrix
here with components 0 1 negative 1 0.
so we've determined the correct inner
product between vial Spinners is PSI
transpose Epsilon Phi where the Epsilon
Matrix equals this
so for two Paulie Spinners xai and Kai
their inner product is Sci dagger Kai
dagger is what we call the Dual spinner
of xai the duel is like the left portion
of an inner product
if PSI is a column that lives in a
spinner space then sideager is a row
that lives in the corresponding dual
spinner space we talked about this in
the last video
for two vial Spinners PSI and Phi their
inner product is PSI transpose Epsilon
Phi
this PSI transpose Epsilon term is the
Dual spinner of PSI
again the Dual spinner is like the left
half of the inner product
if PSI is a column that lives in a
spinner space then side transpose
Epsilon is a row that lives in the
corresponding dual spinner space
so we know the vial spinner in her
product must be unchanged after a Lorenz
transformation so L transpose Epsilon L
must equal Epsilon
if we multiply both sides by L inverse
on the right we can cancel L and L
inverse and see that L transpose Epsilon
can be replaced by Epsilon L inverse
this gives an alternate way of
transforming the inner product where the
second half Phi transforms with L and
the first half PSI transpose Epsilon
transforms with L inverse we'll talk
about this more later in the video
it's also worth mentioning that the vial
spinner inner product is anti-symmetric
and gets a negative sign when we swap
the order of the Spinners and equals
zero when we put the same spinner in
twice
because of this the Epsilon metric
doesn't measure lengths and angles like
most metrics it is more correctly called
a simplectic form but I won't discuss
that in this video
next I'm going to talk about chirality
for Pali Spinners there's no notion of
left chiral or right chiral Spinners but
vial Spinners come in two types either
left chiral or right chiral
the reason for this is that Paulie
Spinners transform with su2 matrices and
there is only one version of su2
but vile spanners transform with sl2c
matrices and there are two copies of
sl2c matrices called the left and right
representations and we can travel
between them using complex conjugation
I'll show you what I mean
if we look at these two matrices you
might argue that they are different
Transformations one rotates in the X Y
plane and one rotates in the YZ plane
but another interpretation is that they
are the same physical transformation
just written in different coordinate
systems
in these visualizations the two physical
rotations are the same but the
coordinate axes are different
to relate to the two matrices we can
change coordinates with C do the
rotation with r and then change
coordinates back with C inverse
the result of these three operations is
the Matrix R tilde which rotates in the
tilde coordinate system
the same thing can happen with spinners
we can have two different su2 matrices
that end up doing the same physical
transformation they only look different
because the matrices are used in
different spinner coordinate systems
for example it's possible that you and U
complex conjugate represent the same
physical transformation just in
different spinner coordinate systems
to show this we just need to find a
coordinate change C which satisfies C
then U then C inverse equaling U complex
conjugate
if we write the Matrix Big C with
entries A B C D and go through the
Matrix multiplications we get four
equations where I've written the
determinant as capital D
matching both sides of equation 2 tells
us small c squared equals the
determinant and a squared equals zero
doing the same thing with equation three
tells us small D squared equals zero and
B squared equals the determinant
plugging all this into the determinant
formula tells us that b equals negative
small C so our coordinate change Matrix
Big C looks like this
what this shows is that U and U complex
conjugates can really be viewed as the
same physical transformation but
represented in different spinner
coordinate systems
it turns out that we cannot say the same
thing for the sl2c matrices that
transform vial spinners
it turns out that there is no change of
coordinate Matrix C which satisfies C
then L then C inverse equaling L complex
conjugate
this means that if we take the sl2c
matrices we're familiar with that do
lorentz Transformations and then complex
conjugate them we get an entirely new
copy of sl2c which is not the result of
a change of coordinates
we call these two copies the left
representation and the right
representation
left chiral vial Spinners will transform
with the left representation and right
chiral vial spanners will transform with
the right representation
so unlike Pali Spinners vial Spinners
come in left chiral and right chiral
versions
finally let's go over the notation used
for the components of vial spinners
now this next section of the video will
involve the placement of indices on vial
Spinners unfortunately there are so many
different index conventions across
multiple sources that the conventions
you see in this video will probably be
different than the ones you find in a
textbook so make sure to pay attention
to the conventions of your textbook and
how it differs from the conventions in
this video
so we've already seen that there are
ordinary vial Spinners and dual vial
spinners
and now we're saying that there are left
chiral vial Spinners and right chiral
bile Spinners so there are actually four
types of vial Spinners in total left
left Dual right and right dual each of
these transform in their own way
let's say that when we do a lorentz
transformation on space time the
components of a left spinner PSI
transform with an sl2c Matrix called l
in this video series I'll denote left
spinner components as columns with upper
indices
the left Dual of PSI is given by PSI
transpose Epsilon remember this is just
the other half of the inner product for
vial spinners
if PSI transforms with L from the left
then side dual will transform with L
inverse from the right
remember the entire point of the inner
product is that it stays the same under
a lorentz transformation
so if one half transforms with L the
other half must transform with L inverse
in this video series I denote left Dual
spinner components as rows with lower
indices
if we take a left spinner and complex
conjugate it we call the result a right
dual spinner right dual vial Spinners
transform with the complex conjugate of
L
in this video series I denote write dual
Spinners as columns with upper indices
that have dots on top
if we look at the inner product of vial
Spinners and complex conjugate the
formula the second half PSI star
transforms like a right dual spinner
with L complex conjugate
for the first half we can rewrite
Epsilon Star as Epsilon since it's real
and the complex conjugate transpose can
be written as a dagger
this must be a right spinner which
transforms with the complex conjugate of
L inverse
this makes sense if one half of the
inner product transforms with L star the
other must transform with L star inverse
in this video series I denote right
Spinners as rows with lower indices with
dots on top
I've summarized all four of the
different vial Spinners along with their
transformation rules and index notations
here
this notation for the four types of vial
Spinners that use both the dotted and
undotted indices is called Van Der
Varden notation
now I should mention something else here
I've written the various vial Spinners
using a mix of columns and rows
some sources prefer to write all vial
Spinners as columns only
to do this we need to take the transpose
of the vial Spinners that I've written
as rows
so if we take this transformation and
take the transpose of both sides this
transposes everything inside the
brackets and also reverses the order
now the transpose of Epsilon is negative
Epsilon but since we transpose Epsilon
on both sides we get Negative signs on
both sides that cancel out and we get
this
so keep in mind how the transformation
rules change when we take the transpose
so in the column only notation the four
Transformations look like this
the reason we refer to left-handed and
right-handed Spinners is because they
are related by mirror symmetry just like
left and right hands
we can reflect space in a mirror by
sending the XYZ basis vectors to the
negative versions of themselves
if we do this rotation Transformations
are unchanged because rotation in the X
Y plane is unchanged when we reverse the
X and Y basis vectors
we can see this in our spinner
transformation matrices as well because
when we flip the signs on the two sigmas
they cancel out leaving the Matrix
unchanged
when we look at how left and right
Spinners transform we know that su2
rotation matrices are unitary so L
inverse equals l dagger this means that
right chiral Spinners rotate with l
dagger dagger which is just L the exact
same rotation that left chiral Spinners
rotate with
however when it comes to lorentz boosts
boosts are hermitian not unitary if we
take the hermitian conjugate of 2x2
boost matrices we get the exact same
thing back
the reason for this is that the Boost
matrices only contain a single Sigma
Matrix and the sigma matrices are
hermitian
when we mirror space this term in the
lorentz Boost does change sign which is
equivalent to reversing the angle in the
Boost and giving us the inverse lorentz
boost
when we look at how left and right
Spinners transform we know boost
Transformations equal their own daggers
so we can ignore the dagger here
now we see that left and right file
spanners transform in opposite ways when
it comes to boosts which is what we
would expect when we reflect space in a
mirror
if we go back to our transformation
formula for a vial vector and Factor the
vial Vector into two vial Spinners we
see the first spinner transforms with L
so this makes it a left-handed vial
spinner
if we take the second half of the
formula and transpose it we see that
this spinner transforms with L star
which makes it a right dual spinner
so a vial Vector can be thought of as
the outer product of a left-handed vial
spinner whose components are written
with upper indices and a right-handed
dual vial spanner whose components are
written with upper dotted indices
as seen in the last video if the vial
vector's determinant is non-zero we can
use the trick shown in the last video to
break it up into a sum of four matrices
and then Factor each of those into a
pair of vial spinners
so in general a vial Vector can be
written as a linear combination of
tensor products of left vial Spinners
and right dual vial spinners
in the last video we saw that a linear
map called Sigma transforms a
three-dimensional Vector into a powly
vector which lives in the space of
spinner dual spinner tensor products
The Matrix entries of this linear map
Sigma are here
similarly we can also use a linear map
Sigma to map a 4D space-time Vector to a
vial Vector which lives in the space of
left spinner right dual spinner tensor
products
The Matrix entries of this linear map
are given here these are called the
infeld van der Barden symbols
as before we see that a single tensor
index can be converted into two spinner
indices using this linear map
the last thing I'll mention in this
video is Dirac spinners
when dealing with spin one-half
particles in special relativity we need
to keep track of both left chiral and
right chiral spinners
when writing them both in column
notation they follow these two different
lorentz transformation rules
it's possible to write the left and
right Spinners stocked on top of each
other like this as a four component
column called a Dirac spinner
the 4x4 Matrix which transforms this
direct spinner is this blocked diagonal
matrix here where the upper 2x2 block
transforms the left spinner and the
lower 2x2 block transforms the right
spinner
Dirac Spinners show up in the Dirac
equation which describes spin one-half
particles in special relativity
including both the left and right vial
Spinners allows for the description of
both matter and antimatter spin one-half
particles but I'm going to leave this
discussion for later in this video
series
so to conclude this video I'm just going
to review this chart of differences
between the Pali Spinners of 3D space
and the vial Spinners of 4D space-time
in 3D space we measure physical length
and we rotate vectors with SO3 matrices
in 4D space-time we measure the
space-time interval and rotate vectors
with lorentz transformations so13
D vectors can be written as 2x2 Pali
vectors that rotate with double-sided
su2 matrices
4D space-time vectors can be written as
2x2 vial vectors and transform with
double-sided sl2c matrices
Pauly vectors can be factored into Pali
Spinners which have this inner product
and vial vectors can be factored into
vial Spinners which have this inner
product
the concept of chirality does not apply
to Pali Spinners and so we only have
spinners and dual spinners
but left and right chirality does apply
to vile Spinners and so we have left
left Dual right duel and right vial
Spinners each with their own different
transformation rules
as an exercise you can take these vial
Spinners and sl2c matrices and see how
the matrices act on the Spinners as a
bonus you can try drawing these Spinners
on the Block sphere from video 5.
also if we assume that these Spinners
and matrices belong to the left
representation try writing out the left
Dual right duel and right equivalence
for these Spinners and sl2c matrices